<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse touching choyce of religion By Sr. Richard Tempest Baronet.</title>
            <author>Tempest, Richard, Sir, 1619 or 20-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T624A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833372</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2066:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse touching choyce of religion By Sr. Richard Tempest Baronet.</title>
                  <author>Tempest, Richard, Sir, 1619 or 20-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n. ,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages stained, with faded print and slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE touching Choyce of RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RICHARD TEMPEST Baronet.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Antiquam exquirite matrem, <bibl>
                     <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Judge yee <hi>what</hi> I ſay, <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:4"/>
            <head>To the Lady TEMPEST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is my Duty to give you an account of ſpending my Houres, whoſe vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous directions hath ſtill enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me the imployment of them in the beſt things: and there can be no endevour comparable to the Inqueſt after Truth. Happy are Mens early imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that moſt worthy miſtres of Mans ſoule; when the Son
<pb facs="tcp:37848:5"/> of their Judgement riſes free from thoſe Clouds and Miſts, which otherwayes by long aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, time, and endevour, they would be but hardly able to expell. I muſt acknowledge my weakeneſſes, and errors, knowing it is the Victory of Chriſtianity, to conquer the Pride of a Mans owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and whoſe vigor is ſhewed in our loweſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions. The World is like that Nymph, which ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thoſe, to whom ſhe moſt ſeemed faire; And Men in
<pb facs="tcp:37848:5"/> the ſhort courſe of life, heape up to themſelves a ſort of Opinions and Paſſions, and make them the faithleſſe guides of their lives, of which though they highly eſteeme, yet doe they but dwell under thoſe barren Hills which are never without Clouds and Showres diſcending thence: And who would for the love of that, which in a moment periſhes, refuſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that, which will beſtow on him Eternity; and in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of all humane things, will render him a felicity ſolid and
<pb facs="tcp:37848:6"/> durable? I ſhall ſhew you what Port my Thoughts have arrived at, to eſcape the ſtormes of Error, and from thence to deſpiſe the ſeverall Winds of Doctrine with which Men are much toſt, but never Saile; and through the diverſity of Opinions, halfe of them Pray for thoſe Winds, whereby the reſt are Drowned. The name of <hi>Rome,</hi> but once Named, ſome Mens minds become ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the apprehenſions of Superſtition, Conſpiracy; and what evills throng not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:37848:6"/> their conquerd Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? whereas they being got out of the Magicke Circle of parties, (where their minds are Conjured with the Devill of Faction) they finde that to be the place, which did commend to the whole World, <hi>The Faith of the Romans.</hi> And where Chriſtian Profeſſion hath with infinite ſufferings and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions triumphed over the Armed Power of its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and foure hundred Hereſies that have ſprung up before <hi>Luther;</hi> ſuch high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures
<pb facs="tcp:37848:7"/> Men have entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thoſe Names which they looking directly on with the Eye of Reaſon, would perceive ingraven the well-drawne Lines of Truth; they by going on one ſide, looking with the Eye of Paſſion, draw the ſame Figures and Lines, by a deceit of the Eye, to beare an unhandſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. We intertaine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion, and the Sacred Word of God (the Records of it) delivered over to us upon a Divine infallible teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb facs="tcp:37848:7"/> which is that of the holy Catholique Church, to which he hath promiſed his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the Worlds end. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Men would inlarge their thoughts, and take a free and open view of all the parts of the Fabricke of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſhall conſider of that power which he hath left to his <hi>Church,</hi> of his injunctions to heare his <hi>Church,</hi> of his promiſes to aſſiſt his <hi>Church; The Gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as a Light upon a
<pb facs="tcp:37848:8"/> Hill:</hi> How great comfort muſt it needs rayſe in the Hearts of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to finde this made good, in a conſtant un-interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſucceſſion of Biſhops from Saint <hi>Peter? Let God be true, and every man a lyar.</hi> The <hi>Church of Rome</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, is but a particular <hi>Church;</hi> but let them not offer affront to the Divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through abuſe of Wit, or Logicall trifle (of a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall particular) for <hi>the Church of Rome hath</hi> ever defended <hi>the Catholique cauſe;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:37848:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> antiquity <hi>hath</hi> aſcribed unto it a more powerfull principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, calling Her, <hi>The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Churches;</hi> though the Holy <hi>Catholique church</hi> is ever the ſame; like the Ocean, <hi>which as it beats upon ſeverall Countries with its Waves, begets ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Names; being now called the</hi> French <hi>Sea, then the</hi> Spaniſh. Thoſe <hi>Madam</hi> who are poſſeſt with prejudice againſt the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> have all different wayes of maintaining <hi>their</hi> oppoſition;
<pb facs="tcp:37848:9"/> neither will they agree to the judgement of any one Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; the ſame Arguments have not the ſame effects with its different enemies; but like Wards in a Key, they are to be fitted to the diverſity of parties, and capacities, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke their judgements, faſt bound with <hi>error:</hi> It being truely ſaid, <hi>That not the perfection of Reaſon, but the proportion doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile.</hi> Some retain ſtill ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the bottome of the Box, and will not let it ſee
<pb facs="tcp:37848:9"/> 
               <hi>the Light</hi> by conference, leſt it fly away; accounting it the <hi>ſureſt tenure of Truth, to ſtick with obſtinacy in the quickſands of error, and eſteeme it their beſt title to it, to refuſe to diſpute it.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Meaſures Truth by the temper of indifferency, <hi>and eſteemes it to be the ſafeſt way to be freed from Error, to be willing to capitulate.</hi> A third frames his own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and by Reaſons and deductions drawne thence, makes all their Diſcourſe agree
<pb facs="tcp:37848:10"/> well enough with it ſelfe; <hi>As Aſtronomers, ſome of them making the Earth to move: ſome the Heavens; and by both Doctrines, according to their principles layd downe, make up their Phai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena, and appearances;</hi> but tell them of Antiquity, Fathers, and the Councels, they will anſwer you with that Merchant, <hi>that hung out for his Signe, Books ſet on fire;</hi> ſo that if any deſired to have been Truſted, or to have come in his Bookes; He anſwered
<pb facs="tcp:37848:10"/> them, <hi>That they were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> ſo if you would get any beleife from them, from Libraries and Bookes, <hi>their Zeale hath already Burnt them.</hi> Another ſort are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily placed, betwixt a Puritan and a Prieſt; <hi>If the Prieſt urge Councels and Fathers, they turne to the Puritan, and ſteale the Bible out of his pocket, to confute him with: And if the Puritan urge the Bible, then he turns to the Prieſt, and borrowes of him the Decrees and
<pb facs="tcp:37848:11"/> Councels, to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with.</hi> Children, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle, call every one Mother; but comming to the uſe of Reaſon, they then acknowledge onely their true Mother.</hi> Thus doe Men beare their ſpirituall Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, dreſt up in ſeverall garbes and formes, and apply to themſelves the benefits of that ſtupendous Miſtery of our Redemption, by the ſeverall Conduits and Channels of their owne Fancies: but God is <hi>both the Way, the Meanes,
<pb facs="tcp:37848:11"/> and the End;</hi> He hath made compleat the deſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Grace, and Men will be found to be more in love with the Meanes, then the End, and to empty all their Zeales and Devotions into ſome new Mode in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or particular Opinion, whereby they are differenced from others: They hold ſuch a courſe, that doe make them ſeem to be deſirous to take our Saviour by the Hand, over the backe of his <hi>Church;</hi> whereas <hi>he hath</hi> ſaid of <hi>his</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:37848:12"/> Embaſſadors, <hi>which</hi> were to continue to the Worlds End; <hi>Who heares not you, heares not me.</hi> But Madam, its more agreeable to you, and more contentfull, to caſt the Lines of ones Thoughts into the ſmooth and pleaſant waters of Devotion, which waſh the beautifull Walls of Sion, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then into the boyſterous Sea of Controverſie, for which my Barke is too little; and I ever returning thence Sea-ſicke: but onely induced <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to give your ſelfe, and
<pb facs="tcp:37848:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſome other of my worthy Friends ſatisfaction: In the performance of which, I ſhall little value the Cenſure of thoſe who ſuffer themſelves to be carried away with that eaſie fault of Fault-finding; And doe beſeech your Ladyſhip to give me your Bleſſing:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt humble, and moſt obedient Son, <hi>R. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:13"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP.</hi> I.</head>
               <p>COnſideration of Religion, under the Notion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations.</p>
               <p>Wherein is diſcourſt, of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall of their Tempers and Opinions, and perticularly of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP.</hi> II.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 29. againſt Melatair.</note>An Anſwer to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of that grand Objection, repeated in the Words of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Bramhal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If you ſeeke to obtrude upon us the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, with its Adherents, for the Catholique Church, excluding three parts of
<pb facs="tcp:37848:13"/> foure of the Chriſtian World, from the Communion of Chriſt; Or, the Opinions thereof for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and Fundamentals of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Faith: neither our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor our Religion, nor our Charity will ſuffer us to liſten to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Wherein is related the Opinion of Antiquity: Of the neceſſity of keeping communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. How Proteſtants agree, and how they exclude one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Catholique Church</hi> excludes none, but whom their owne errors exclude.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Of the uſe of Reaſon, in the Election of Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:37848:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP.</hi> III.</head>
               <p>A View of ſome of the chiefe Doctrines, pretended to be the cauſe of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Praying to Saints.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Images.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Praying for the Dead, and Purgatory.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Confeſſion and Satisfaction.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Of Fre-will.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP.</hi> IV.</head>
               <p>The falling away from the Church (under the Notion of Reformation) the cauſe of troubles of State: and from the ſame grounds they build
<pb facs="tcp:37848:14"/> their opinions on, ariſes the grounds of the diſturbance of Governments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Wherein is declared the ill and unfortunate ends of thoſe, who in ſeverall Ages and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, oppoſed the juriſdiction of the Sea of</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>True Religion, no Enemy to Governments.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP.</hi> V.</head>
               <p>An Invitation of Wits to the Study of Arts, and to leave oppoſing the Church; (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,)</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Of the excellency of the Fruits of Piety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That they proceed onely from true Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:15"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37848:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. I.</hi> Conſideration of Religion, under the Notion of Reformations.</head>
            <p>THe eſteeme and value men put on the finding of what is <hi>Truth,</hi> makes all men ſo plauſibly vent their perticular Opinions, under the Notion of <hi>Reformation;</hi> ſo that by the gate and entrance of that word, mens underſtandings are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into an inextricable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth of <hi>error;</hi> and no ſooner men withdraw their wary ſteps
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37848:16"/> from one deluding path, but they are inſenſibly conveyed into another, and doe but ſtill by the variety of falſhoods, tend to the Center of thoſe Maeanders: nor is there any way to get out of thoſe toyles, till by a neglect of all thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall fences, that each party incloſe their opinions with, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing the Laws of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes; men redeeme themſelves into the liberty of a diſ-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted judgement, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the name of <hi>Calvin,</hi> or any perticular opinion, or nationall alterations hath ſhut up with prejudice. There are ſufficient Alarums to hearken to that precept, <hi>of trying all things:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37848:16"/> and as it is ſaid by one of the Fathers, the Church ſhall never be free from two ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; outward affliction, to try mens affections to God: and errors in faith, to try their right knowing him: but I perceived men ſubject and tide to any party, or to men of perticular opinions, riſe to no further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, then of ſuch Tenents and Articles, which thoſe men are Patrons of, who cry up the Champions of them, and are wholly frozen in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards thoſe, who uſing the freedom of their reaſons, make a retreat from their precipices. <hi>Grotius,</hi> the glory of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Learning, eminent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37848:17"/> through a univerſal knowledge, and who drew his experience of the ſtate of Chriſtendom, at the Fountain head of great affairs, imployed all his <hi>Junior</hi> ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for reconciling Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and bringing them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one band of government; yet in the later deliveries of his judgement, acknowledges that an impoſſibility, and that there was a neceſſity to return to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique obedience, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as a Rock againſt which hitherto, all Hereſies had beat themſelves into froath. He made me with more equall eye look upon the ingenuous retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Doctor <hi>Vaine,</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37848:17"/> 
               <hi>Creſſey,</hi> againſt whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I had an edge for deſerting that, which as I thought, ſhould have centred all judgements and devotions; but after finding them fetch from deep ſearch of antiquity, their reſolutions of returning to that Church (from which the ill accidents and obliquity of late times had miſled men) with reluctancy I found their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies true, and my moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling underſtanding, their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons moſt imperiouſly brought to capitulate; finding, that though men profeſſe to become ready captives of <hi>Truth,</hi> yet they are unwilling to think, but that they are in its fetters all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37848:18"/> wherefore I obtained of my ſelfe, to diſcharge all pre-ingaged affections, all byas of Faction, and intereſt; reſolving to pay that Homage to my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, which I ſhould finde he required of me; knowing, that when he commands a Sacrifice, nature muſt ſleep, affections be ſilent. I found this likewiſe a great deale more plauſible to my ſelfe, than eaſie with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to put in practice. I perceived that a conſtant and ſteddy Judgement was required to enter upon the quarrellings of Polemick Diſcourſes, where were uſed ſo much ſubtilty in arguing, partiall proceeding, ingenious diverſion (where wits
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37848:18"/> were imployd for conqueſt, ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the advantages of Language and Science) not for to be rewarded with the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of <hi>Truth,</hi> but to beare the Lawrell, for having conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red men with words, though not ſatisfied them with reaſon. Wherefore I conſidered the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, between what may be ſaid, &amp; what ſhould be thought: and therefore to diſcharge that duty which a man owes his own reaſon, for the utmoſt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſcrutiny of <hi>Truth,</hi> I conſider'd the Foundations and Authorities upon which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parties at the ſame time did challenge mens devotions. 1. The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37848:19"/> and ingeniouſly profeſſing to be more convinced by, then tyde to the Fathers, or Antiquity; equall their owne Interpretations and Preachings to the dignity and verity of the Text, extolling and crying up their imaginary diſcipline; to the meanes of ſetting up of which, they ſacrifice all Morall, Civill, Eccleſiaſticall obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, counting it want of Zeale in Gods ſervice, to be true in any relation, when for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the Covenant, it is expedient to be failing in them; this is their invention, to which they aſcribe an <hi>Apotheoſis;</hi> they dreſſe it up, and adorne it with Scripture Phraſe, making the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37848:19"/> two Attributes of Gods, Mercy and Juſtice, (all the threats and promiſes of either) but to damn and crown mens forwardneſſe or ſlowneſſe in this cauſe, in titling to Divinity this their deluſion; with ſuch heats doe they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, what was never heard of in Gods Church this fourteene hundred yeares; and this doe they extoll to be the height of Reformation. 2. All other ſects and ſorts that diſcent from them, who will not be ſubject to this ſpirituall bondage, have their bucklers of defence out of Scripture too (the meaſure and judge whereof is their own interpretation) they alledge, <hi>That when two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37848:20"/> together, God is in the midſt of them:</hi> whereas the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay in their Expoſitions, <hi>That when two or three of the Church are gathered together for devotion ſake, God is in the midſt of them;</hi> not that the gathering of two or three together doth make a Church; thus in the Son of Gods Word, doth ſwarmes of gnats and flyes play, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being governed: And though both theſe Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be contrary to each other, yet both oppoſe a third Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, eſtabliſhed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Laws, which retained a ſolemnity of Forme and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, and from its firſt angry leaving onely, to acknowledge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37848:20"/> the Authority of the Roman Biſhop, fell by degrees to leave off one thing after another. And as it ſerved them, to be able to bandy againſt the Church of Rome, complide with thoſe other reformiſts (as they call themſelves) who in no other thing agreed with them, but in diſagreeing from it. Its owne proper temper ſtood not upon termes irreconcilable, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the cauſe of new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines received in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to be that which forced their departure: the moſt inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and ingenuous, owned this Modell, whoſe parts I high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem, whoſe perſons I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, having had eſtabliſhment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37848:21"/> of civill authority, decency of Ceremony, and Forme of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy. I endevoured to obſerve in the Writings of the chiefe upholders of it, their freer and leſſe compeld judgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church of Rome, ſuch as fell from them in the intervals of their calentures, &amp; heats of contradiction. I found the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> againſt M. <hi>Fiſher</hi> acknowledging, that if they were another <hi>Church</hi> from the Church of Rome, he would ſoon return to it. <hi>Hooker</hi> denies to damne them, who have been the authors of their ſalvation. Others part ſtakes betwixt Truth and Faction, ſaying, <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath the truth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37848:21"/> in it, as Silver lying hid among Rubbage.</hi> I have heard a Learned Biſhop yet living, confeſſe, <hi>All the difference was onely in words and termes.</hi> Thus doe they date their Religion a new, from ſome accidentall thing, bringing in new Epochaes and accounts from changes and alterations, (which they terme Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) whereas the firme princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Church, was ever a pleading an uninterrupted ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, of Paſtors and Doctrine from the Apoſtles time to this: Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaying in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, He hath not Eccleſiaſticall Ordination, who keeps not Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical union; but they have cut this Scepter (which whilſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37848:22"/> whole, every one did bow to) into contemptible little coyne, which are ſeverall parties, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring different impreſſions, which are onely currant with thoſe, whoſe perticular marke and character is ſet upon it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. II.</head>
            <p>A <hi>View of the whole Queſtion betwixt the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Epiſcopall party, by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the perticulars of that grand Objection, which I repeate in the words of Doctor</hi> Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 29. againſt Molatair.</note>
               <hi>If you ſeeke to obtrude upon us the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, with its adherents, for the Catholique
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37848:22"/> Church, excluding three parts of foure of the Chriſtian World, from the communion of Chriſt:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Opinions thereof for Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles and Fundamentals of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Faith; neither our Reaſon, nor our Religion, nor our Charity, will</hi> ſuffer <hi>us to liſten to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doe they Patronize their oppoſition to the Church of Rome, under the challenged protection of Religion, Reaſon, and Charity; and with as great applauſe as the naming of theſe things can afford, they celebrate the triumph of error. They be few words, I confeſſe; but ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37848:23"/> as govern and conſtitute all the actings and reaſonings of man, by their light, and influence. But to Write over the Doore where the Plague is, all the Medicinable names in Phyſicke, will not preſerve men from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: onely the greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is, that men more eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of good things, are deceived into places of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: And becauſe this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſeemingly is framed up, and upheld by all thoſe things, that are worthy of man. I will leave pecking at ſtones in the field, and will impartially view the inward ſtrength and force of this building. <hi>They finde fault that any ſhould obtrude upon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37848:23"/> them, the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, with its adherents, for the Catholique Church, excluding three parts of foure, of the Chriſtian World, from the communion of Chriſt.</hi> Who is it that would obtrude the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, with its adherents upon you? is it onely in this age urged by a Faction? Who is an enemy to your moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Reformation, and for am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and profit ſake, will not apply themſelves to the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and purity of Gods true Religion? Is it obtruded onely by thoſe, whom you have juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended, warranted thereto by the Laws of God, and the Church? Is it by thoſe onely, who by their erronious tenents
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37848:24"/> makes juſtifiable your depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from them, and bandying againſt them? to returne to them again, were, to forfit your zeale in Gods cauſe, to betray your Reaſon, Religion, and Charity; but if on the contrary it prove onely a perverſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to maintaine a Sciſme; if it be onely your calumny, and ill dealing with your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from whoſe lap, peeviſhly, and without reaſon you have withdrawne your ſelves; if it be you onely who take ſcandal at the Church, which can be none to you, though they may be to it, <hi>Tunc alta ruunt ſubductis t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cta columnis;</hi> then have you Paſſion for Zeale, Opinion for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37848:24"/> Faith, and confuſion for the effects. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iraeneus,</hi> who lived in the ſecond age, in his Booke againſt Hereſies, reckons up a ſucceſſion of the Biſhops of Rome, from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> to the Pope then preſent, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces it neceſſary for all Churches, to hold communion with thoſe that adhere to the Church of Rome; <hi>Ad hanc enim Eccleſiam, propter potentiorem principalitatem neceſſe eſt omnem convenire Eccleſiam, hoc eſt omnes qui ſunt undique fideles, in quâ ſemper ab his, qui ſunt undique, conſervata eſt ea, quae</hi> ſit <hi>ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis traditio; fundamentis igitur Eccleſiam Apostoli, Lino Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum,</hi> &amp;c. then were they plain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37848:25"/> and poſitive, in the declaring the duty of all, to deſert all perticular Churches, which did not adhere and hold communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Sea of Rome. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> of the ſame Age, <hi>De pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptione Hereticorum,</hi> ſi <hi>autem</hi> Italiae <hi>adjaces, habes</hi> Romam, <hi>unde</hi> &amp; <hi>nobis auctoritas praeſto eſt.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of the fourth Age or century of the Church, <hi>How happy is that Church, upon which the Apoſtles have poured out all Doctrine with their bloods.</hi> Saint <hi>Jerom</hi> of the ſame time, upon the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, The Church which is the houſe of God,</hi> notes upon it thus; Of which <hi>Damaſus</hi> (then Pope) is at this day ruler: And againe, <hi>Primà
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37848:25"/> adverſus</hi> Ruffinum, <hi>fidem ſuam quam vocat; camque qua Romana pollet</hi> Eccleſia; <hi>Si</hi> Romana <hi>reſpondent, ergo Catholici ſumus.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of the fifth Age, <hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>contra</hi> Faunſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um, <hi>Vides in hac re quid</hi> Eccleſiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae <hi>vale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t authoritas quae ab ipſis fundatiſſimis ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum uſque ad hodiernum diem, ſuccedentium ſibi met Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſerie, populorum conſenſione firmata.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Jerom</hi> of moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere life, a profound Schollar, and generall Linguiſt, lived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, a Monke, a Prieſt, ſaid Maſſe. St. <hi>Augustine</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Hippo,</hi> confeſſedly a Prieſt, and offered up the body and blood of Chriſt in Sacrifice, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37848:26"/> the living and the dead. Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> a Monke, Prieſt, unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; did not they all live and dye in the communion of the Church of Rome, and did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sciſme? I remember one told me at <hi>Venice,</hi> pleaſantly diſcourſing of the difference which that Republique had with the Pope; We would have become (ſaith he) any thing to have been <hi>ad oppiſitum</hi> with the Pope, <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Calveniſts,</hi> but that we were ſatisfied with the truth of all opinions of the Church; from our own Records which have been in violated and kept intire, and delivered then with as great vigor, as now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, for about a thouſand
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37848:26"/> years; which time that City hath ſtood, never taken, or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd, nor burnt; the two great winding ſheets of humane things. Will not the Laws and conſtitutions of all ancient go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments declare and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the ſame, even of thoſe places which have revolted from them? muſt all men in ſo many grave Councels, reſorting from all parts of the Chriſtian world, relating one to another, what in the ſeverall places whence they came, hath been held, and ſo from time to time an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall eſtabliſhment of ſuch things as have been found to be the generall Traditions and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church: and yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37848:27"/> muſt all theſe be thought to have walked in a vaine ſhadow? Rocks, Cities, Woods, muſt be thought to move, while their eyes dwelling too much upon the currant of the times, breeds this deception, that they are thought to move from the little Boats, when it is the Ship boats departing from them. Thus it is evident, who thruſts the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> upon them, and what hath thruſt them from the <hi>Church of Rome?</hi> When parties are once engaged, though teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies be as lowd as Thunder, yet the ball muſt be kept up; poore pretences muſt undergoe the opinion of inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; all ſticks ſeen in that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37848:27"/> Water, muſt be crooked: <hi>Non perſuadebis, etiamſi perſuaſeris:</hi> They ſay, <hi>It muſt not be obtruded upon them as Catholique, it exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three parts of foure, of the Christian World.</hi> All Chriſtians in all Ages have pronounced that Artikle, <hi>I beleeve the holy Catholique Church;</hi> if mens ſaith ſhould not vary, the object muſt never faile; and in all Ages downe from our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours time, they have moſt ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly pronounced this Artikle in the boſome of the Church of Rome; which taken locally, is but a Pariſh Church; but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of retaining with others that ſame Doctrine which the Apoſtles St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37848:28"/> delivered them, whether by writing, or by word of mouth; in that ſence, it is called <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique;</hi> and ſo, <hi>Orbis in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe eſt.</hi> When Hereſies ſprung, <hi>as there muſt be Hereſies,</hi> they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſtill to what was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by way of Doctrines to them, wherby they did repel all falſe and erronious opinions, as conſtantly maintain their own Doctrine. When diverſe parts of Scripture were called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, it was the <hi>Churches</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority did pronounce them Divine: now the <hi>Church</hi> was to be deceived in its Sentence, or not: If it was then infallible, why not now? and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation and expoſition, as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37848:28"/> well as the Letter, when Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is not Scripture, but rightly Expounded. As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an externe and adventitious condition of the Church, it ſuffers ſometime dilatation and inlargement; other time, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and contraction, yet ſtill ever the ſame. The Arke, that was the type of the <hi>Church,</hi> vvas ſometimes on the Waves, ſometime in the Wilderneſſe, travelling: againe, in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in peace and glory. When the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie had ſo catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſurprized the World, no doubt but the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> did exclude them; and becauſe it vvill not now let every ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puddle of Opinion, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37848:29"/> every infectious currant of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction run into its Sea; or that like the Sea, it will not let any dead or corrupt thing lye in its bowels; therefore forſooth, it muſt not be obtruded upon any as <hi>Catholique, it excluding three parts of foure of the Christian World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it ſhould have ſo much good nature, to admit all, its Doctrine would not be <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique,</hi> that is, what was profeſt at all times; the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church is but one. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy is but one, ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> as Streames from the ſame Fountain, Branches from the ſame Root; here is nothing but that fidelity, which a Spouſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37848:29"/> owes to her Betrothed, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of Forraine loves, or unlawfull mixtures. Thoſe that are called, Reformiſts, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude not one another; when they would appear a great body of opponents of the Roman Church, they exclude them not from oppoſing the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, though in manner, and in their own opinions they oppoſe and exclude one another; like that Image, part whereof was Clay, part Iron, that by clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving together reſembled a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, though never incorporated.<note place="margin">Harmony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions. <hi>B. Hall</hi> of the Churches of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and France.</note> They are enemies of a good Catholique malice, whilſt they would unite all the different Formes of Sciſme, wherein eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37848:30"/> ones Fancy was their guide, and of theſe would make an angry union, to gratifie their humour of oppoſing their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church: and if one ſhould lend a ſevere aſpect into their own Commonwealths, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, he ſhall ſeem to retreave the ancient Chaos, each Sect ſo differing from other, and every one diſſenting from what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were at firſt: When they ſhak'd hands with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> every one departing a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall way, according to the concernments and ends of their Leaders, or the Genius and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the People, or the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents &amp; affaires of thoſe times, which ſteared their furies, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37848:30"/> indignations. The <hi>Lutherans</hi> hold the <hi>Calveniſts</hi> for the Phaetons of Europe, and in a late Sinod have condemned them guilty of all the Warres and diſaſters in theſe late times. <hi>Calvin</hi> allowes of Epiſcopacy, yet his followers make it ground enough of an immortall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, to have them extirpated. In every Country, that ill Seed that <hi>Calvin</hi> ſowed, came up of a different faſhion; as he well perceived, who deſcribed their ſeverall humors of Genevizing, Anglizing, Scotizing. What Wars are rayſed in the mutuall oppoſition of each others Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, every one of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome perticuler Opinion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37848:31"/> wherein they magnifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being their <hi>Eurika;</hi> and ſets it as it were in the Van, for an Enſigne of the Faction, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they doe ſo peeviſhly militate? A Satyre would be the beſt ſtile, to deſcribe the animoſities, they proſecute each others Opinion with, and no leſſe would it become all thoſe angry fits, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe in their ſeverall wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings and errors: they throw a Sea of gall and bitterneſſe after thoſe, who upon mature exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, relinquiſh thoſe Mazes, they leade their followers in. What ſhould one ſpeake of the fruitfull Independency, big with all ſorts of Opinions,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37848:31"/> Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Zwinglian, Aecolampadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and all theſe the Engliſh Church Proteſtant, Epiſcopall baniſhes &amp; excludes from them. The boſome of the Catholique Church is ſpread wide, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine all, whom with earneſt Prayers and endevors, it invites and deſires, zealous of their ſalvation, which onely in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way, is to be had there. The ancient Heretiques, <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Neſtorians, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tichians,</hi> whoſe reliques yet poſſeſſe ſome place in the World, are excluded likewiſe by themſelves, who make this objection; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their owne Reformation, hath been a varied unconſtant
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37848:32"/> one; that except they <hi>would</hi> (fal in love with this Word Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) I know not well what can be underſtood by it. <hi>H.</hi> 8. firſt onely threw out the Pope, but retained the ſeven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: after, by degrees, they were taken away, and new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines brought in, with relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and ſometime it hath been wholly ſubmitted to the Presbyterian humour, in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly going to their Churches; and ſo generally uſing their Directory: whereas, according to their own opinions, vvithout Biſhops no Ordination can be; <hi>Quo teneam nodo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They complaine, <hi>That the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37848:32"/> opinion of the Church of Rome, are obtruded upon them, for Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles and Fundamentals in Faith.</hi> Doth not all the Wilderneſſe of their opinions, their opiniotive Idolatries, each one avouching their Doctrine, with, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord?</hi> Doth not all their Anarchies and irregularities, flow in upon them, by letting thoſe antient bulworks goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to neglect, which ſtood betwixt a Sea of error and themſelves? that is, in ſtead of ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the old wayes, to view and diſcover truth from: they have onely diſdainefully trampled upon them; and in ſtead of asking the Fathers, to ſee vvhat they held and thought; they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37848:33"/> will make bold to thinke the Fathers miſtaken, if they finde themſelves contradicted by them; and hold, and thinke of them, as not worth asking. Thus doe they diſcountenance Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the eſtabliſhments of the Church. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>When he ſhould come, he would order things:</hi> Now, ſaith the Father, what hath beene univerſally obſerved, was orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him. St. <hi>Auguſtine de Bap. contra Donatist,</hi> That which the Univerſall Church holds, and is not Inſtituted by Councels, but alwayes retained, its probably beleeved, not to be delivered, but by Apoſtolicall authority. Their error that oppoſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37848:33"/> of the Church, and the prerogative of the Apoſtolicall Seat, flowes from this wretched pudled Fountaine; that is, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Reformation to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture it ſelfe, interpreted by mens perticular judgements.</hi> The holy and ſacred letters, are the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed records of our ſalvation, Celeſtiall Meſſages, Angels of peace, winged with love, which hover over mens ſoules, with celeſtiall protections, comforts, and graces: they are the glaſſe, wherein is beheld the beauty of holineſſe, the ſplendor of the Eternall Father, the Image of his Sonne. Yet as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith, The words of the Scripture, are to be ſo underſtood, as the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37848:34"/> world hath beleeved, which it ſelf foretold ſhould <hi>beleeve: they</hi> were writ upon ſeverall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to perticuler Churches, which faithfully kept, what was committed unto them, whether <hi>by writing,</hi> or by word of <hi>mouth;</hi> the Scripture confeſſing, <hi>That if all had been writ, the world would not have contained the Books:</hi> and every where they enjoyne the hearkning to the <hi>Church,</hi> which who ſhould not heare, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from Chriſtian commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by their holy cenſure. The Church was then eſtabliſht, when divers of theſe ſacred let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were directed to them; and by them, and what other rules were delivered &amp; taught them:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37848:34"/> they governed, taught, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, corrected, and abſolved; ſo that they were like the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in the Arke: the <hi>Church</hi> of God, had the cuſtody and interpretation of them; ſo that who ſhould Sacrilegiouſly ſteale the teſtimony out of the Ark, and run away with Scripture, and impaile Congregations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with new goverments, and cry, <hi>The Word of the Lord,</hi> and quarrell at the other orders and Traditions of the Church, he would be judged by all, to have raviſht the ſpheares of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to have diſordered the Divine diſpenſation of his goodneſſe towards us: Neither can they pretend any right over
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37848:35"/> thoſe Laws, who are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thoſe Laws Waters out of their own channels, beget ſtrange and forraine taſts; and this is the grand and unhaypy ſophiſtry of this age; <hi>a bene conjunctis, ad male diviſa.</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture divided from the <hi>Church,</hi> ſeems to countenance every party in their fancies, making it like a Looking-glaſſe, wherin they doe but ſee their owne Image, not Gods; and by an inward deluſion, view the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of their owne wits, flattering their underſtandings, whilſt by a foreprepared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, they finde ſome counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to their own inward thoughts: Whereas Scriptures,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37848:35"/> the Oracles of God, are truth; not the Pen, or the Preſſe, being writ becauſe they were true; not true, becauſe they were writ.</p>
            <p>They ſay, <hi>neither their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Reaſon, nor Charity will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to acknowledge the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>for their Mother.</hi> I ſhall now view the uſe of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in the election of Religion, and ſee if it well directed, doth hinder them. When that which flows from well eſtabliſht au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ſhall be call'd in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, or diſputed through the violence and diſorder of Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the upholders of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, have recourſe to the Origens and Fountaines
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37848:36"/> of Juſtice; ſhewing how all their Acts and Decrees, received their obligatory nature, from the agreement they had with thoſe rules of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Laws which conſtituted them to be good and juſt: ſo that they who before found onely the effects of peace, by a due obedience to them, now ſearch into the reaſons and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, why they were of ſuch power, to produce ſuch effects: And thoſe who before pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lived in the building, labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly now ſeeks the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The myſteries of Religion being above reaſon, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with mirakles, which are above nature: but whether
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37848:36"/> this, or that Religion, be the ſame with that which was ſo confirmed, muſt be examined according to all thoſe rules, which though divinely given, muſt now by reaſon be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether they be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to them, or not. The protitipe was from Heaven, the originall ſupernaturall; but for to prove the continuance of it, we muſt compare, and examine it according to all that hath been delivered concerning the ſame formerly. And its no ſmall difficulty to chaſe <hi>truth</hi> through its ſeverall channels: The Laws of Gods <hi>Church,</hi> challenge our obedience; the oppoſing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Sciſme, becauſe we are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37848:37"/> kept in one intire body, by the obſervation of them: the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect whereof cuts us off from that communion. Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments and Policies have their Acts and Statutes, the oppoſing whereof makes men guilty of ſedition and faction; becauſe there is a ſolution of continuity made, and a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them into parts, which threatens deſtruction of the whole; the preſervation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is the end of all good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. The Laws of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> diſtinguiſh Vice and Vertue. What way is there to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Eccleſiaſticall obedience, from Sciſmaticall combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? but to prove the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37848:37"/> of the <hi>Church,</hi> its conſtant ſucceſſion, with the exerciſe of its juriſdiction: and that thoſe, who have ſeperated themſelves from it, bears a later date, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun from ſome accidentall change in Government; the Pride of their Leaders, or the ignorance and heap'd up errors of the people. What differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Vice, and Vertue? not a locall diſtinction, of being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the midſt of Vice; but, as ſuch actions obſerve the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of right Reaſon, which aſſignes them their end, their degrees of heats and motion. Who views not the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ancient Common-wealths in their firſt and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37848:38"/> Laws, their Records, Acts of State, and a conſtant exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of a Supreme Authority? When men with the armes of reaſon encounter the deſert ſoules of Atheiſts, doe they not prove the Impreſſion of a Deity ingraven on the ſoules of all, though they erre in paying their Homage? Doe they not bring reaſons from ſeverall Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, for the demonſtration of <hi>à natura naturans,</hi> or firſt mover, or Supreme Governor? Thoſe who prove the truth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion againſt <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> doe they not pleade the innocency and ſimplycity of thoſe men, that firſt Preached <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified; that they could
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37848:38"/> have no end, but the hope of an Immortall Glory to beare them out in all their ſufferings; they deliver'd a Doctrine to the world, an enemy to carnall pleaſures, and the ambition of the world; and with diſarmed innocency to prevaile over the furious malice of their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, muſt needs prove an om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power that ayded them: and having brought them to the acknowledgement, that God is the Author of our Faith, then they finde a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to receive the ſpeaker, for a full demonſtration of the truth of all that is ſpoke:
<q>
                  <l>Then doe they all to heavenly rules give place</l>
                  <l>Which paſsions kill, &amp; reaſon doth deface</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37848:39"/> The <hi>Church</hi> is builded upon the Divine promiſes, <hi>That the gates of Hell ſhould not prevaile againſt it:</hi> and we ſee, that neither Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, whoſe angers are Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres; nor an Angel of Light-ſeeming falſhood, hath prevailed againſt his <hi>Church;</hi> neither the courſes, nor diſcourſes of mens Pens and Wits, have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent againſt it; <hi>In hanc manca ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fortuna.</hi> It hath continued in the Succeſſion of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty Popes; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Sibils</hi> Propheſie, <hi>The Fiſhers hooke hath ſubdued the Roman Empire, and conquered the World,</hi> verified in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors. Thus Reaſon may have its ſatisfactions, and hath a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37848:39"/> latitude of diſcuſſing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing active in thoſe things which are its proper ſpheare, which are arguments of credibility: the light of nature will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct us a great way in our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which we may carry in our hands, till they be obſcured with the clearer lights of grace. A Starre conducted the Wiſe Men to the Sonne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: and though illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations from Heaven, ſometime beate downe the fierceſt <hi>Saul</hi> to the ground, that is at once to make them humble, and to know his will: and though ſometimes by his omnipotent grace, he, as it were, caſts his ſervants at once in a mould; as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37848:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37848:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37848:41"/> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was called <hi>Apoſtolus fuſilis;</hi> yet reaſon otherwhile, (which is Gods Law too) muſt be ſummon'd up to our ayde, whilſt by degrees we recover our falling ſteps, and unwinde our ſelves out of error: <hi>Hos quaeſitum munus in uſus;</hi> Is there any way to weane mens minds, nurſt in the imbraces of error, but the imployment and uſe of their reaſon? To diſcover what their opinions owe to their cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, what to a rationall exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: men beare an affection to opinions, as to the places where they were borne, though it be the rude rugged moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Swiſſes. The ſoule with difficulty parts with its
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37848:41"/> firſt imbibitions, and with pain climes the riſing Hill of Truth. Many are the innate deluſions of mens ſoules: occult adheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſecret faſtneſſes, which are not caſſierd till their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are informed from what ſource they ſpring, till by the thred of reaſon, they unwinde themſelves out of that Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, nature, or their firſt courſe delivered them into: Mens judgements ſuffer from ſociety, and example retorts upon our underſtanding. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and Affection, are me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums which repreſent things different from their true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions: nothing can infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe mens minds, or ſet them
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37848:42"/> free from thoſe inchanting im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, but the Power and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of Reaſon:
<q>
                  <l>Stultus non accipit, verba prudentiae,</l>
                  <l>Niſi ea dixeris, quae ſunt in corde ejus.</l>
               </q> Now, as Reaſon compels them to return to the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo will the tenents of their own Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, if great ſoule-killing opinions be not found to make the Gulph, and the <hi>mega kaſma.</hi> Some perticulars whereof in the next Chapter I ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and then I hope their Charity is ſuch to themſelves and others, that they will be as good as their words. Thus in a ſhort Map, I have let you ſee, <hi>That the Church of</hi> Rome,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37848:42"/> 
               <hi>with its adherents, doth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily challenge their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with, and obedience to, by the Voyce of Antiquity, which hath ſtill kept its ancient depoſited Doctrines, written and unwritten, whoſe boſome is ever open to receive all, but whom their owne Sciſme and Error excludes; and that both their Reaſon, Religion, and Charity command a returne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. III.</hi> A View of the perticular Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, pretended to be the cauſe of their not returning.</head>
            <p>THe juſt exceptions againſt any opinion, is either want
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37848:43"/> of Truth, or want of Piety: but they being <hi>convertibilia,</hi> I ſhall ſhew, That as theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines excepted againſt are true, ſo likewiſe they have the Impreſſions of God ingraven on them; though there be two pretences of exception that they make. Firſt, Objecting to generall Councels, new creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Truths, when they doe no more then declare what are ſo. Nextly, From the words they make uſe of to condemne Error and Hereſie. They would have it, that the Councels make new Artikles, when as they pretend to ſignifie no other thing by thoſe words, then that which is certainely knowne to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37848:43"/> be the Ancient, and Orthodox Doctrine. The Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (ſo called) thus ſtands in oppoſition, and is a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and a negative one, and is an angry and verball conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, oppoſitions of Science falſely ſo called. There hath not wanted thoſe in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that have exactly tride the depths of all thoſe ſtudies, whether in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Languages, for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Text in the Originall, or of Hiſtory, or Schoole-reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherein any opponents can pretend to conteſt with them in.<note place="margin">Convect Lond. 1562. Art 16.</note> If they will appeale to Scripture, as ſometimes they doe, how many Catholique
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37848:44"/> Champions have faithfully ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the literall ſence, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, the Hiſtoricall part, the Parabolicall, the Figurative ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, the Naturall, the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals of the Old and New Teſtaments, the Hebrew and the Greeke, with the Antient Greeke and Latin Gloſſes. If Hyſtory may prevaile, <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſhall bring teſtimony, <hi>Palladius, Sezemen Socrates, Ruffin</hi> ſhall be witneſſes. St. <hi>Bede,</hi> St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſhall tell what was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes in the firſt times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. If the pious Decrees of thoſe Popes (which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beleeve to be Saints in Heaven) ſhall be heard, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Doctors have viewed all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37848:44"/> their Decrees, both before the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and after. If conqueſt, by the Arts of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, be pretended to, they have enterd into the niceſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and have been cutters of a Commin Seed: and are throughly acquainted with all the moſt retired advantages of Wit and Learning. There have been many and great challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the foure firſt Generall Councels, <hi>Nice, Constantinople, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Calcedon;</hi> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholiques have not onely read from the firſt of <hi>Nice,</hi> to the laſt of <hi>Trent,</hi> but alſo all other approved Provinciall Councels. If the Fathers, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and men famous in all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37848:45"/> Ages, be conſulted with, they will appeare to be all of the ſame holy Catholique Church; St. <hi>Baſill,</hi> St. <hi>Athanaſius, Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory Neſſen,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, <hi>Iraeneus, Cyprian, Fulgentius, Pamphilus</hi> the Martyr, <hi>Palladius, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, Ruffinus, Lactantius, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius, Lyrenenſis, Dioniſius</hi> the Areopagite, Schollar to Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Clement,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine, Hierome,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe, Papias</hi> Schollar of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, &amp;c. Who will not then put their foot into the ſame <hi>Barke,</hi> with ſo excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to ſayle to happineſſe in? but remaine in the <hi>Cock-Boars</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37848:45"/> of their owne private opinions, to be toſt with every wave of Doctrine, and to ſuffer <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke?</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Scriptures, are preſerved by the <hi>Roman Church</hi> (defendors of the Catholique cauſe. Its Doctrines whether writ, or delivered by mouth, Hiſtorians deliver the ſame to be with, what Popes have maintained, Decrees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, Expoſitions cleared, Councels declared, Schooles taught, and Fathers delivered. And their practice is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by all Ancient Laws of <hi>England,</hi> Imperiall, Nationall of Forraigne Countries, and former times: by confeſſion of Enemies, <hi>Mahumetans, Jews,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37848:46"/> Pagans,</hi> and all thoſe Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, who confeſſe Antiquity is not for them. I ſhall for thoſe opinions, that are pretended to be cauſe of their departure, and the hinderance of their not returning againe to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> give you a taſte of the Fathers in ſeverall Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: and withall ſhew what fruits of piety, charity, and comfort they have contain'd in them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Euchariſt Altars, &amp; Sacrifice.</note>The word <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> muſt not be indured; they ſay it is but a late word,<note place="margin">The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of its Doctrine.</note> ſince the Councell of <hi>Laterane</hi> onely uſed; hence they impute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty to the Artikles of the <hi>Church:</hi> they acknowledge the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37848:46"/> 
               <hi>Church</hi> hath a power given it, to decide controverſies, and the truth of the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence being called in queſtion, with ſubtile interpretation of words, the <hi>Church</hi> muſt uſe ſome words of art to oppoſe them, and ſecure the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their nimble turning of the ſence of words; ſo that to quarrell at the word, is indeed to quarrell at the exerciſe of the <hi>Churches</hi> power; moderne rebellions againſt the Tenents of holy <hi>Church,</hi> forceth it to uſe ſome words, to hinder the evaſions of its enemies, which they profeſſe to ſignifie no more by, then what was taught, by <hi>This is my body.</hi> The word Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37848:47"/> was not uſed, till Councels found it neceſſary to oppoſe certain Hereſies of thoſe times, by framing that word. But what a ſiniſter laying hold of all occaſions is there, by thoſe who once undertake to defend a party? Ingenuity is fled, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the Pilot, whilſt they are toſt upon thoſe faithles Seas of error. <hi>Tranſelementation</hi> is as hard a word, and M. <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi> allowes that. The <hi>Greeks</hi> uſe a word to of the ſame ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, yet no offence taken at it. Heare the Fathers ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall expreſſions, as well as late Councels. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the fourth Age after Chriſt, <hi>by the benediction, nature it ſelfe is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37848:47"/> changed; the change is not made by Faith alone, but really,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome. Not every bread, but that which receives the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, is made the body of Chriſt.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the fifth Age.<note place="margin">In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Melatei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſſe, That Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity hath uſed the expreſſions of ſeeing Chriſt, touching Chriſt in the Sacrament, of faſtning our teeth in his fleſh, &amp;c. What ſatisfaction can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with a moderate ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, which one ſhall not meet with in later Schoole-men and Councels? <hi>Clypeus Tridentinus</hi> ſaith, Beleeve Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the manner of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiating, you need not.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37848:48"/> Schoole termes oblidge not, whether by adduction, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, or any other words of Art, they may argue, but not diſturb the Faith of the <hi>Church.</hi> How Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament, can neither be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſenſe, nor imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquin. Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias Patriarcha</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> ſaith, By the power of the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſpirit, the bread is changed into the very body of Chriſt, wine into the very blood. The Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> declares, that in this Sacrament, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> true God, and true Man, is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, really, and ſubſtantially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under the ſpecies of thoſe ſenſible things, yet nor
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37848:48"/> according <hi>to a naturall manner of exiſting, but Sacramentally.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>He was the Word that ſpake it,</l>
               <l>And what that word did make it,</l>
               <l>I doe beleeve, and take it.</l>
            </q>
            <p>All the Ancients uſe conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without flaſhes of Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, or tranſlation of words, the word ſacrifice, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to note, giving of thanks, but propitiation: oblation and offering likewiſe are uſed by the Fathers of the Councell of <hi>Nice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dialog. 4.58.</note> This ſacrifice ſingularly ſaves the ſoule from Eternall deſtruction, which doth repaire unto us by miſtery, the death of the onely begotten; who although, riſing from the dead, dyes not, and death ſhall have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37848:49"/> no further power over him; notwithſtanding in himſelfe immortally and incorruptibly living, is againe ſacrificed for us in the miſtery of this holy oblation. Fathers in all Ages have ſpoke and held this. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Perron</hi> calls it a ſacrifice applicative of a ſacrifice. Thus doe the enemies of Catholique Doctrines and words, by their oppoſition of them, make that, which ſhould be the band of Unity, the flag of diſſention. And for the name of Altars, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, He is upon the Altar, who ſuffered for all thoſe under the Altar (the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Martyrs) who are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by his Paſſion. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37848:49"/> ſaith, the ſacrifice it ſelfe is the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is not offered to the Martyrs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they themſelves are that alſo.<note place="margin">The pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and fruits is brings.</note> The word <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> truely underſtood, affords us the comfort of aſſerting the truth of Gods promiſes: For the ſeverall modes and manners which thoſe out of the <hi>Church</hi> fancy to themſelves, touching the preſence of Chriſt, if there were words of Art to expreſſe, how detractive would they be found, from the verity, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, and reality of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which our Saviour inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? But Catholiques doe adore the Lord Jeſus, here true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37848:50"/> preſent; onely him doe they adore, who although, till the world be diſſolved, after a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall manner, he is above; yet here with us, is the truth of the Lord, <hi>That as often as we receive, we eate his Fleſh, and drinke his Blood,</hi> without which, <hi>there is no life in us;</hi> by which Union, how doe our ſoules receive a torrent of joyes and graces, which flow from a Celeſtiall ſource, into all the faculties and powers of our minde, ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to him, who is our head, being incorporated into him?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Invocation of Saints.</head>
               <p>Whilſt we live in the earthly Tabernacles of our Bodies, we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37848:50"/> are ſubject to the ſumes of fleſh and blood, to the Impreſſions of diverſe affections, and the clouds of the world; whence we are put to execute a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and act a vigilent part againſt the depths of Satan; and to that end, we deſire one anothers Prayers; And ſhall theirs be leſſe effectuall, whoſe bleſſed ſoules are unbodied, out of a poſsibility of falling, and enjoying the bleſſed preſence of God, inflaming with charity and good will towards us? They rejoyce at our converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; they underſtand our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: holy <hi>Church</hi> hath ever practiſed to make them friends in the Court of Heaven: To
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37848:51"/> obtain their requeſts of their King and ours, the effects of Chriſts mediation and merits, may be more hopefully purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Angelical Petitions, then mans diſturbed and cold devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom: de Martyr: Egyp.</note> Let us aske the Fathers, and they will tell us, By the Prayers of the Martyrs, we may after our departure hence, ſee and imbrace them, ſaith ſaint <hi>Chryſostom.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>Mary</hi> praies for us, ſtronger then <hi>Deborah,</hi> more powerfull then <hi>Jael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Cog. nit: verae vitae.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, When you call upon the ſaints in Prayer, it behoves you thus to thinke of them, as placed in the glory of the Eternall beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, moſt glorious lights, farre
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37848:51"/> out-ſhining the Sonne, who have fully all that is good in the Viſion of God, and who forcibly aſſiſt all that call upon them. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Heliodore,</hi> After death (ſaith he) you ſhall pray for me, who have incited you, that you might overcome. In the Liturgy of <hi>Baſil,</hi> Now Martyrs earneſtly pray, that God may grant us remiſſion of our ſinnes.<note place="margin">De vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, The Angels are to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon in our behalfe, who are aſſigned to us for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And againe, let us not be aſhamed to have them the Interceſſors of our infirmity: of the Interceſſion of the bleſſed <hi>Virgin;</hi> Doctor <hi>Don</hi> ſaith pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37848:52"/> Her Wombe was a ſtrange Heaven, for there God cloath'd himſelfe, and grew; our zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thanks we poure, as her deeds were our helps, ſo are her Prayers; nor can ſhe ſue in vaine, who hath ſuch titles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.<note place="margin">The pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and fruits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Whilſt men make themſelves ſuch ſtrangers to the Inhabitants above, they break the communion of ſaints: if mens joyes were all above, if men did thirſt after thoſe glorious fruitions, they would accept of all the helps that might leade them to it. In in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating, and worſhipping the ſaints, we worſhip him, whoſe ſaints they are: Saith a Father, in often contemplating their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37848:52"/> crownes, and begging their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, how are our hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed through their helps? it erects our thoughts on high, and gives us courage in our journey below, to have ſeen all the dangers of it conquered, by thoſe who as they were our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſo now are our Patrons.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> It inlarges and mends our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, when we view thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Inhabitants ſhining all as ſtars of ſeverall magnitudes; one glorious in the ruddy beams of Martyrdom; another ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the ſnow white purity of Chaſtity; others, now the higher, by having been low in their own eſteeme: they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke us, by viewing their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37848:53"/> to the care of acquiring their vertues; neither let any pretend, and ſay, <hi>God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to call on him,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>its needleſſe to goe to any other;</hi> for he hath told us, <hi>He heares not every one that cryes, Lord, Lord, but him who doth the will of his Father;</hi> and his will is, that we ſhould be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and hearken to his <hi>Church,</hi> and not in ſtead of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving its commands, revile it, and rent, and teare it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of its Doctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Confeſſion, Abſolution, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</head>
               <p>This is, and ever hath been, ſo univerſally, generally deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, Preached, urged, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37848:53"/> in the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> that none can deny it, but thoſe whoſe ſtiffe-neckednes will not give the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leave to look back into any Antiquity, or Fathers; theſe words are plainely, frequently made uſe of, to expreſſe this part of the Diſcipline of the Church, which the Fathers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The vigor of the Goſpel;</hi> as if without it, all mens man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and courſes towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, would languiſh.<note place="margin">Sermons of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions.</note> Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> from the Text, <hi>Whoſe Sins yee remit, they are remitted;</hi> acknowledges a perticular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Confeſſion to be ment, by reaſon, he ſaith, it is expreſt, <hi>whoſe Sins,</hi> not <hi>what Sins ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 55.</note> Let us heare Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37848:54"/> expreſſe himſelfe againſt thoſe that oppoſed it, It is indevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (ſaith he) that ſins may not be redeemed, by ſatisfactions and juſt lamentations, that mens wounds may not be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with tears; true peace is taken away, by the lye of a falſe one; and the healthfull boſome of a Mother (a ſtep-mother interceding) is ſhut up; weeping and mourning ſhould be heard from a ſinner, and the face of thoſe who have falne.<note place="margin">Auguſt. Hom. 5.</note> Let him come to the Prieſts, thoſe by whom the Keyes are diſpoſed of in the Church; and let him, from thoſe who are ſet over thoſe holy rites, receive the meaſure of his ſatisfaction.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37848:54"/> 
                  <hi>Tertullian de poenitentia, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio ſatisfactionis conſilium.</hi> It is objected, that its an all-da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring preſumption, to pretend to be able to ſatisfie in the moſt pure eyes of Almighty God, and ſo plauſibly run on in an ill applide humility; when a man doth, what anothers demand is, its ſaid, he hath ſatisfied his deſires: nay, if the Creditor doe for ſome reaſons, forgive the Debt; he is ſaid to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: and its ſpoken by reaſon of the Evangelicall compact, when God by promiſing, makes himſelfe a debtor, ſaith the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and we doing what is required, that is, <hi>bringing forth fruits worthy of Pennance,</hi> and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37848:55"/> performing ſuch expreſſions of ſorrow, and thoſe penitentiall injunctions as the <hi>Church</hi> wil be ſatisfied in, for the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our hearty repentance, it is cal'd ſatisfaction: but whom the expreſſions of the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> will not ſatisfie, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, he is ſicke of ſiding and parties, nor is any deſire of peace with the <hi>Church</hi> preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Seſsio. 14 cap. 8.</note>Its agreeable to the divine clemency, leſt ſins be pardoned us, without any ſatisfaction, occaſion being taken, that we lightlier eſteeming of ſins, fall into more grievous ones, injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and contumelious to the holy ſpirit of God, treaſuring
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37848:55"/> up wrath for us againſt the day of wrath; for without doubt theſe ſatisfactory puniſhments, doe greatly recall us from ſin, and, as it were, with a certaine bridle reſtraine us, and make penitents more cautious for the future; they cure likewiſe the reliques of ſin; they take like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe away ill habits got by viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous living, but contrary acts of vertues: nor at any time is there a ſurer way in Gods <hi>Church</hi> to remove puniſhments, then that men frequent theſe works with true griefe of mind: and it draws to this, that whilſt we by ſatisfying ſuffer for our ſins, we are made conformable to Chriſt Jeſus, who ſatisfied
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37848:56"/> for our ſins, enjoying alſo the moſt certaine earneſt; that if we ſuffer together with him, we ſhall likewiſe be glorified together with him. Neither is this our ſatisfaction ſuch, which we pay for our ſins, that it is not made by Chriſt Jeſus: for we who of our ſelves, as of our ſelves, can doe nothing; yet he co-operating, who ſtrengthens us, we can doe all things: ſo man hath not whence he may glory, but all our glorying is in Chriſt, in whom we live, and merit; in whom we ſatisfie, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthy fruits of pennance, which have their force from him, and are offer'd from him to the Father, and by him are
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37848:56"/> accepted of the Father.</p>
               <p>It was ever held in the <hi>Church</hi> of God the ordinary means of the forgiveneſſe of ſins, and is ſo farre from being a cauſe to drive men from the Catholique Church, that to enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of it, they ſhould come with humble minds, and teares in their eyes, to beg the comfort of this onely approved ſure way for their pardon. St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> in his <hi>Enchirid.</hi> ſaith, God hath given liberty to none to ſin, though by his pittying of us, he blot out our ſins, if ſitting ſatisfaction be not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
               <p>How wholeſome muſt it be for our minds,<note place="margin">Fruits &amp; Piety.</note> to diſcharge
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37848:57"/> themſelves, to ayre our minds by confeſſion, to have the ſtate of our ſoules judged of, (all men being partiall cenſurers of themſelves) and thence fitting Phyſicke preſcribed, after his inſpection of our inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion? what comforts are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into our breaſts, in liew of all vitious affections or acts we part with thence in Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? our pardon is confirmed in Heaven, as it is granted here on Earth. How many thicke and foggy ſelfe-deluſions, falſe opinions, deſperate feares, ill grounded doubts, doe all vaniſh from that ſoule, that hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed thoſe clouds by cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Confeſſion? What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37848:57"/> of graces, ſpirituall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions, healthfull directions are acquired? here is exerciſed an act of that moſt acceptable humility, in throwing your ſelfe down at the Feet of Gods Embaſſador, in deteſtation of your ſelfe; exerciſing your Faith likewiſe, in beleeving that, <hi>Whoſe Sins they remit, they are remitted,</hi> this being the ſecond table after ſhipwracke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Purgatory, and Praying for the Dead.</head>
               <p>It is the generall confeſſion of thoſe, who call themſelves the <hi>Reformed,</hi> that Prayer for the Dead was anciently uſed; ſome few teſtimonies of which Ile ſhew you. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37848:58"/> his Booke <hi>pro Mortuis,</hi> writes, <hi>That if no where it ſhould be read in the Old Teſtament, yet the authority of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Church is not ſmall; which is ſo cleare in the cuſtome of this, where in the Prayers which the Priests poure out to their Lord God at the Altar, a recommending of the dead hath place alſo.</hi> And the ſame Father, <hi>ad Laurentium</hi> in the <hi>Enchiridion, There is a certaine manner of living</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not ſo good that it doth not require theſe things after death; nor yet ſo ill, that theſe things may not profit him after death. Aerias</hi> was condemned of the whole Church, for condemning this. One may perceive by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37848:58"/> practice of the <hi>Church,</hi> how theſe Texts in Scripture are to be underſtood, <hi>of being neither pardoned in this World, nor in the World to come:</hi> And that other place, concerning thoſe, who build hay and ſtuble upon the Foundation; <hi>they ſhall be ſaved, yet as by Fire.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, ſaith <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi> is a purgation of ſinnes with glory. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, That the recitall of the names of Martyrs at the Altar, is more that they may pray for us, then that we may pray for them. For the pains in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; one cannot conceive how there ſhould be a Purgatory, without ſuffering pain. Heare
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37848:59"/> what <hi>Boethius</hi> ſaith a thouſand yeares ſince, <hi>But I pray</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>remaine there no puniſhments after this life? yes, great certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (ſaith he:) <hi>for ſome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I take to be exerciſed with bitter puniſhments,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Liber 4.</note> 
                  <hi>others with element purgations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fruits &amp; pietie.</note>To a Skoffer, there ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want matter; but as he ſaith, <hi>Cave ſed fiat nè Jocus iſte Focus:</hi> When S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tryall by fire, its blowne away with a hundred light In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations: an Atheiſticall ſpirit would quarrell with that expreſſion, <hi>of the damned gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their teeth;</hi> which, they ſay, is an effect rather of cold, then of fire. But as a Father ſaith,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37848:59"/> 
                  <hi>Hereſie is not from the Scripture, but from the ſence of Scripture, which the Church, by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, ſafely preſerves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It muſt rayſe no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts in the minds of thoſe, who have parted with what were their joy here, to be able by devout Prayers to recommend them to a more advanced ſtate of Joy. It doth inlarge the ſubject of our charity, whilſt death it ſelfe doth but quicken our devotion for our Friends, parting with them, as men not without hope. It ſweetens our paſſage hence, being not out of the pertaking of the benefit of Prayers, Almes, and the good Works of thoſe we leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37848:60"/> the <hi>Communion of Saints:</hi> and for the effects that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of poſtumous and after ſuffering muſt have upon the minds of men, it muſt needs tend to the making the ſoule diſguſt theſe inferiour appetites and affections, which breathe upon the ſoule an earthy vapor and fouleneſſe, which it muſt be cleanſed from, with penall purgation, before it can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into thoſe purer joyes, to ſee God, which only is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them that are cleane of heart. The perverting, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordering the diſpenſation and application of Gods grace, who (though Gods merits be all-ſufficient, and our Redemption
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37848:60"/> compleat, and the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes large) yet thinke, that notwithſtanding, all their life time, their judgements have been abuſed with the too great eſteeme of the empty delights and glories of the world, their wills following the impulſe of carnall pleaſures, nor any Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall ſparke ever kindling their affections; yet by a ſwimming fancy in the head, that Chriſt hath dyed for them; thinke, they ſhall preſently jumpe into Paradiſe; It is a merry conceit: ſo was it of that Foole, That thought, that all the ſhips that came into the Harbor, were his owne. <hi>If we ſuffer together with him, we ſhall likewiſe be glorified
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37848:61"/> with him,</hi> was held to be the ſureſt earneſt of Everlaſting Joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Free-will.</head>
               <p>He who hath made you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your ſelfe, will not ſave you without your ſelfe, ſaith a Father. God is the way, means, and end; all is from him, and to him: but how much more noble thought have they of the Deity, who conceive him to deale with man as endowed with <hi>free</hi> operations, then with us, as with ſtockes and ſtones, that are meerly patient? It is the meere grace of God that gives good works their force and value; yet no ſuch neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that any thing is done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37848:61"/> man will or no:<note place="margin">Apolig. Epiſt.</note> For who could either prayſe, or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that, who can imagine ſuch actions to be rewarded, or puniſhed? or that ſoule to be immortall, and performe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which ſhould want <hi>free</hi> and reaſonable actions, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and pledges of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: but we are to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the wiſedome of Gods <hi>Church,</hi> which agreeth the aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſcience of God, with the temporall co-operation of man; that it leaves the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and yet proveth the temporall action, appetite and delight, or conſent to any thing to be voluntary, free, and in the power of man, to be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37848:62"/> or omitted, rewarded and puniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the uſe and Veneration of Pictures and Images.</head>
               <p>Upon this is waged a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall warre; <hi>Hic illius arma, hic currus fuit.</hi> The Reformiſts ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally take it for Idolatry, and what ever is ſpoken againſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry in Scripture, they preſſe and urge upon the uſe of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. But before they tax our Mother with ſo odious a crime: they might pleaſe to conſider the nature of the objection, and how farre the extent of it is: and withall, they might conſult the opinion of ancient
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37848:62"/> devout Fathers (who would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have loſt a thouſand lives, then have committed Idolatry) touching it; and withall, they might have conſidered the uſe of them, before they ſhould be frighted from their Mothers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome (a place of protection) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wandrings and errors, where are layd the ſnares of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Church</hi> ſtory informes us, That the ancient Chriſtians would fall downe before the Statues of the Emperors, which was then the manner and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture uſed to doe reverence; as ſometime to be bare before the Cloath of State, doth ſignifie the like; though they would rather dye, then ſalute ſo the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37848:63"/> Images of the falſe gods. But for the like poſtures to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to be uſed to the Pictures of Saints, or of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, none can ſhew a prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for thoſe outward ſignes of honour ſignified by geſture, are indeed common towards God,<note place="margin">Grotius.</note> Angels, and Men; no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular one being ſet a part, or commanded to be peculiarly uſed, to ſignifie onely Divine Worſhip: when we frame a thought of that good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard in our minds, if we would deliver it in writing, why might we not write it in Hyreogli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies, as well as Letters, which are not ſo ancient, no other thing is ſo worthy, as the mind
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37848:63"/> of Man? but if the Image of our Saviour Crucified be there drawne and viewed by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; why may not our corporall Eye, behold it drawn on Paper, or other materiall, ſince they doe but ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and revive thoſe former Ideas in the mind, which other objects might diſtract, or ſteale away? And by ſeverall Perſons the ſeverall Attributes of God may be ſignified; as a King for Royalty, &amp;c. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, in the Viſitation of the ſicke, <hi>There is added upon the Croſſe the Image of a Man; humbly imbrace this, and weekely venerate it.</hi> The honour done to the Image, is refer'd to whoſe Image it is,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37848:64"/> ſaith <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chriſoſtome.</hi> I know theſe things are propoſed in vain, to thoſe who will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no other Tribunall, then their own breaſts, who exerciſe an Arbitrary and Tyrannicall power over the Conſciences of their followers, whom an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary expoſition of ſome dark propheſie of Anti-Chriſt doth unhinge their minds and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from off, what they ought to turn on, which is obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Authority ought to binde in the luxuriant and forward imaginations of mens owne braines: But I have onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in theſe few perticulars, without uſing any illaqueation
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37848:64"/> of Arguments, or finneſſe of diſcourſe. Thus are all the Churches Doctrines, Practiſes, and Ceremonies, advancements and meanes to Salvation and Piety, the eſtabliſhment of its regiment on Earth, of Pope, Patriarchs, Arch-Biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts, Deacons, ſub-Deacons, Exorciſts, Lectors: where the miſtery of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is ſo eſteemed, and remembred, that no Holy day, no part of Divine Service is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated, but repreſents to us one benefit or another: no Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony in the holy Sacrifice, no action of the Prieſt, no Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Attire he weareth, no Benediction he gives, no Signe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37848:65"/> of the Croſſe he makes, but hath its religious ſignification, and Preacheth to us, and ſpeaks nothing but Chriſt Crucified: therefore, though the great worke of our redemption may be thought not to be hindred, by oppoſing things of an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour nature; yet it is no ſmall matter, the oppoſing the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Church,</hi> tending to the diſſolving that power,<note place="margin">Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths dialogue</note> by which the greateſt things are maintained. Common-wealths puniſh with death a ſmall ſtealth; becauſe its an offence againſt the nature of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Heretofore men proved Doctrines to be true, from the authority of holy <hi>Church;</hi> and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37848:65"/> now they would annull her au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from her Tenents; and from her Articles, would throw durt in her Face, as if ſhe had loſt her being, for being the faithfull Keeper of what was committed to her, and had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited her breaſts, the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for feeding us with their milke.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. IIII.</hi> The falling away from the Church (under the Notion of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) the cauſe of troubles of State; and from the ſame grounds, they build their opinions on, ariſes the grounds of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of Governments.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Church</hi> being Divinely Founded, as it hath ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37848:66"/> all the malices and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the greateſt Tyrants, its enemies; ſo have thoſe, who breaking of that Eccleſiaſticall league which kept them in the limits of the practice, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of the ſame things, miſt of that inlargement and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſſe of commands, which they expected, by altering the ſight and mark, they took their ayme by; they have ſtraide the moſt, from what they chiefly took their ayme at: whilſt they ſought a perticular proſperity, ſeperated from the peace of the <hi>Church;</hi> againſt which, the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterd, forces of mens malice, and Hells fury, became ever weake and impotent.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:37848:66"/>
            <p>The blood of the firſt Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the fruitfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt of the <hi>Church;</hi> their Aſhes were Generative: all the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conflagrations, ſackings, and ſpoylings of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> by the <hi>Goths, Huns, Viſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goths, Halaricus,</hi> were like ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my winds, whoſe Gole and end was onely to dye and expire; while <hi>Rome</hi> triumphed over their ſpoyles, in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that never fayling <hi>Church:</hi> I will not name <hi>Attila,</hi> nor <hi>Limprandus;</hi> the one reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from <hi>Rome</hi> by Saint <hi>Leos</hi> means: the other by Pope <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charies,</hi> ſtrangely and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly. Thoſe barbarous <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens,</hi> whoſe rage was glutted
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37848:67"/> with the conqueſt of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Emperor, the glory of whoſe armes and conqueſt of <hi>Candy</hi> increaſed; who made <hi>Africa</hi> feele the effects of the advancement of their Armies, and ſtrucke terror into a great part of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> who deflowred faire <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſet fire to the Suburbs of <hi>Rome.</hi> And yet againſt <hi>Gregory</hi> the fourth, the Sea of their incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, found its bounds, that its waves ſhould goe no further. The Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> (ſaith <hi>Fox</hi>) died cenſured, being ſlain in the aſſault of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Faith hath ſtill prevailed, in ſpight of <hi>German</hi> Sciſmes, or the powerfull oppoſitions of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37848:67"/> 
               <hi>Dalmatia, Slavonia, Bulgaria;</hi> or the entertainement of <hi>Luthers</hi> diſſoluteneſſe in <hi>Dania, Suevia;</hi> or <hi>Calvins</hi> ſubtilities in <hi>Zelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Franciae, Genevah,</hi> and all other blindneſſes and powers of the reſt of the world. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> dyed with a, <hi>Viciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Galileae,</hi> thou haſt overcome ô Galilean, meaning our Saviour. The <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Emperors oppoſed, and were confounded. The <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, Armenians,</hi> and <hi>Grecians,</hi> are under the Tyranny of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, whilſt they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obedience to the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> How many Pagans Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors before <hi>Conſtantine</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and almoſt all dyed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably. Foure hundred Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37848:68"/> before <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard Lutzen. catalog. Haeret.</note> whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice was all daſht into froath upon this Rocke? How many of the Kings of <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Portugal, France.</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors have been miſerable, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſlaine, who have conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with this Sea in its juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.<note place="margin">Bede, lib. 3: 4: 5. hiſt.</note> Like ſucceſſe had thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, who oppoſed the Faith of that Sea: ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſubmitted, and became re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men; and thoſe that were Apoſtates, miſerably put to death. The <hi>Britiſh</hi> Kings, diſobeyed <hi>Rome</hi> in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and manner of ſhaving of the Crownes of Prieſts: a leaven thouſand of their Munks, who defended
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37848:68"/> this oppoſition, were wrapt up in the ſad cataſtophre of being ſlaine by the Pagans ſword; their Country maſtred, and awed by their hired ſouldiers; and of Kings over them, were made ſubjects to them. Upon the ſtage of every Kingdome, theſe parts have been acted, and have concluded in direfull Tragedies; from whoſe every parcell and paſſage in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors life, <hi>Edwards, Henries, Richards,</hi> the obſervation of men might ſtore themſelves with moſt ſtupendous exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their ſufferings, in, and from their conteſts with the Roman Sea; the revolt, defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and falling away from
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37848:69"/> which, I ſhall ſhew to be preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the unheard of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, diſtractions, wars, and tumults, which threatens ſuch fatall trepidations and concuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the bowels of all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne States: and as effects which are included in their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo all theſe evills to be ſhut up and vertually contained, in the principall, upon which their departure from Rome is made: propoſitions, which ſeemingly blauſible, yet the higher they get into eſteeme and reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo much the more powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doe they ſhowre downe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their followers, deſolation &amp; deſtruction: one may behold them at firſt like little Aery,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37848:69"/> ſoft and tender ſtrings exhaled and aſcending, drawn with the more <hi>powerful</hi> aſpect of the Son: yet, with you ſhall ere long, find deſcending upon you in hard, condenſed, thunder ſtone, with wild flaming expanſions, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of the wombe of that cloude that bred it; or like the woodden horſe, peaceably at firſt let in, yet ſtreight filling the Towne with bands of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men. <hi>A way certainely</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>which ſeeming right in a Mans owne eyes; yet the end thereof is death.</hi> I will firſt take a view of ſome of their perticular opinions, and ſee what a dangerous influence they have upon Governments:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37848:70"/> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> teaches, <hi>That the Lawes of the Magiſtrate doe not binde the Conſcience. Luther</hi> Preaches, <hi>That it is the nature of the Goſpel to rayſe wars and ſeditions among Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that there is no hope of remedy, till all humane Laws be taken away: and</hi> (then that which is the Foundation and ground of all, Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo called) <hi>that all things are to be ſetled, ordered, changed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their agreeing, or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with Scripture, the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation whereof must be the perticular judgements of private Men.</hi> This rule is equally ſtrong for all ſides; too ſtiffe to recant, or yeeld to others judgements: and this ſame rule muſt patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37848:70"/> as many opinions &amp; ſects, as the various fancies of men bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in Scripture can invent or ſuggeſt: thus naturally flowes from this rule of <hi>Reformation,</hi> not onely diverſity of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, various judgements, and oppoſite Doctrines; but ſtrong and numerous parties, that cry up ſuch a man for their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or imbrace ſuch an opinion for their Faith: ſeverall bodies of conſiderable ſtrength, whoſe obligations are the defence of ſuch opinions. New and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall intereſts, whereby every one ſtudies their owne preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and upholdings, though never ſo contrary to each other, or deſtructive to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37848:71"/> where they live: ſo that thoſe who in a contemplative way, and abſtracted conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did but lately talke of the purity of the Goſpel, of light and truth; finde themſelves by and by, plunged in all practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, turbulent, ſeditious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, oppreſſive: A wrong prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in the underſtanding, doth not onely multiply notionall abſurdities, but begets and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces ſiniſter actions: theſe numbers of men, of ſeverall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions and Doctrines, comes to be variouſly planted and ſpread, in ſeverall Countries and Governments; whether brought in by way of Traffick, negotiating one with another,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:37848:71"/> or that ſuch men being bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their own Countries, they ſow their ill ſeed in others Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; or whether the errors be native, and ſprung up there; or that, as infection, they catch and ſpred, by way of example and imitation; yet thus the world becomes to be blended, and the ſubjects in all ſorts of Governments, get a new <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile</hi> to their Allegiance and duty; and inſtead of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the good of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity where they live, they are buſied in the advancing of that body, which for conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and holding the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents with them, they become concerned in: ſo that if in one
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37848:72"/> Government, a ſort of them be oppreſt for their ſeditious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes; preſently in all others, thoſe of the ſame opinion are alarumed: ſo that Governors ſtreight finde their Laws ſilent, diſtractions multiplying; and none ſecured of their owne ſubjects, who doe either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſely throw away on their confederates, that treaſure and mony (which ſhould be the ſupport of their own Country) or if thoſe opinions have taken hold of active and generous ſpirits, which endevour ſtill to make others of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, preſently they expect Forraine ayde and help, to change their proper policies
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37848:72"/> and Governors. Then through the innate reverence that all people beare to the opinion of Divinity; beleeving that the ſpirit moves upon the Face of their Preachers watry diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they become powerfull, like the winds, to make the people as the Sea, ſwell and become unpeaceable, whilſt each ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt other, and all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State: thus are all the veins of Chriſtendome fil'd with theſe unwholeſome and noxious humors, whilſt Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Hereſie often ſhake hands together; for Ambition ſeeks but under any pretence to procure the affections and ſervices of men, and to apply
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37848:73"/> them to their owne uſes: and now ſo great bodies of men, wanting but countenance, and great perſons to be their head, and encourage them; theſe two ſeek their mutuall ends in this conjunction: no diſcontented or ambitious great one, but hath a prepared way to awe, or be revenged on his Prince, or State: and Kings, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors themſelves, are at laſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to hang their Crownes and Diadems upon the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and upholding on one party or other, who becomes ſtrong or weake, as that party ebbes or flowes; all the reſt eſteeming themſelves but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by their power, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37848:73"/> would at laſt prove like the Ivy, which firſt diſſolves the Wall, and then ſeems to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it. Thus did <hi>Reformation,</hi> (ſo called) <hi>Jehu</hi> like, drive its war-like Chariots through <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many; Mars</hi> ſo long a time, ſeeming to have ſet up his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard there; whilſt repleniſhed with theſe unwholeſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, the <hi>German</hi> Diets became not ſo wholeſome, as before: and no leſſe ſuddainely hath thoſe ſparkes taken hold, and flowne over the <hi>French</hi> Stables, whilſt <hi>Genevah,</hi> the Lady of the Lake, challenges the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Apoſtolicall Seate, and dictates Laws to its Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. From <hi>Calvins</hi> Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:37848:74"/> the <hi>Switzers</hi> cantonize their Religion, as well as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: and not meanly have theſe ſeeds grown up under the ſhade of <hi>Orange Tree:</hi> The <hi>Dane</hi> with graver pace, recedes from their former Eccleſiaſticall league; and now all breaking up and disbanding, the face of <hi>Europe</hi> which was ſeen one and intire in the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> is now by theſe numberleſſe Fractions, but parcels and peeces, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting ſeverall Faces, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred anchor of Religion being moved,<note place="margin">True re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, nor prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> all the ſhips of States and Goverments, come to be toſt and troubled; Religion being like the Sunne, which whilſt it keeps its owne proper
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37848:74"/> and heavenly courſe, gives light and influence to all; but when the pretence of it ſerves earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ends, it cauſes a conflagrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and is a <hi>Phaeton</hi> to ſet the world on fire.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</head>
               <p>True Religion muſt be ſuch, that it carry no diſtruction to Common-wealths, though it laſt for ever, as the worſhip of Chriſt was inſtituted to doe. There are vices of men, and there are vices of times; but diſobedience to Governments, or Doctrines of diſloyalty are deteſted by the Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Canons and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the <hi>Church.</hi> I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37848:75"/> the words of an <hi>Engliſh Jeſuit,</hi> This Prieſthood which is now rejected, is the ſame which was given to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtles; the ſame which St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates had, that converted <hi>England;</hi> the ſame which hath been honor'd of all Kings ſince; the ſame Sacrament, unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; the ſame power of order, the ſame juriſdiction: there is not any poynt of civill regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that Sacrament, being wholly ſpirituall and ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall; nothing concerning a temporall Common-wealth; no renouncing or deniall of any authority in <hi>England;</hi> no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy to Prince, no authority
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37848:75"/> communicated, but to offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, to Pray, to Preach, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Sacraments. The <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>Germans,</hi> and other people, having their Doctrine diverſe to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> have their ſeminaries in the ſame City, and their Prieſts maintained by the ſame Popes; yet the Princes of thoſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the greater part being <hi>Infidels, Turkes,</hi> condemne not their Prieſts for Traytors, but admit the exerciſe of their Function, as agreeable to the Common-wealth: and as it were a great abſurdity to ſay, that the Pope in relieving the Catholique Students of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Grecia, Armenia,</hi> and ſuch
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37848:76"/> Nations, ſhould doe it in hope to be temporall Lords of thoſe Countries, but onely for love to true Religion; ſo is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable he ſhould have any ſuch intent in <hi>England,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable as the other to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his temporall regiment: no Article we defend, Prayer to the Saints, Prayer for the Dead, reſtitution for wrongs and injuries to thoſe that live, obedience to Governors, the validity of their Laws, the force of good works; the number, grace and reverence of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, pennance, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſin, both in life and after; teaching duty to God, honour to Magiſtrates,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37848:76"/> equallity to all, injury and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to none: the chiefeſt poynts of true regiment, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be offenſive to a well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red policy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CAP. V.</hi> An Invitation of Wits, to the ſtudy of Arts, and to leave op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Church; with the excellency of the fruits of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which onely can proceed from true Religion.</head>
            <p>IT is obſerved by the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Lord <hi>Virulam, That in Divinity there was nothing to be added by the wit of Man: and in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:37848:77"/> ſtead of finding wantings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratars, complained here of too much luxuruancy of Mens brains; for God hath ſo ſurely founded his Church on one ſide, and the Devill hath ſo</hi> buſily <hi>in the night ſowne Tares on the other, that there is no imployment here for the reſtleſſe agitation of Mens heads.</hi> It was truely obſerved by another, <hi>That Men muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſolve their Religion into Reaſon, or Authority: if into Reaſon, then they muſt beleeve no more then they can prove by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. If into Authority, It was apparant where it had continued this ſixteen hundred yeares; but the meaſure of truth is many times the maintaining Mens cauſe; but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37848:77"/> not truth the guide of their cauſe: they transferre and ſend the beams of their wit, to gild the clouds of their error. How unhappy are the triumphs of thoſe endevours, which ſtrive to make falſhood appeare more like truth, then truth it ſelfe?</hi> As the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poët, deſcribing truth by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na,</hi> which is ſtill one, and the ſame: and falſhood by <hi>Dueſſa,</hi> which is doubleneſſe: complains,
<q>
                  <l>Though <hi>Una</hi> was as faire, as faire might be,</l>
                  <l>Yet falſe <hi>Dueſſa,</hi> ſeem'd as faire as ſhe.</l>
               </q> When the edge of wit is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſide to maintain an error; how are men uncharitable to Texts of Scripture? how doe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:37848:78"/> they pretend to a Genealogy, by thredding all the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever was in any Age againſt the Church, on the line of their Diſcourſe? for their ſervice, ſuch and ſuch Ages muſt have the plagues of <hi>Egypt</hi> brought upon them, groſſe darkneſſe. The Fathers muſt pretend to no more knowledge then that which hath now the approbation of mens more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined braines: and the lately found out rules of (Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo called) muſt over-rule the witneſſe of Antiquity, the Authority of Councels, the conſtitutions of the Church. When <hi>Ireneus,</hi> and St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> &amp;c. doe magnifie the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37848:78"/> Seat, they muſt be held but flaſhes of Rhetoricke, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes with their Pen; they make uſe of hard niceties, elaborate thinneſſe, weake fineſſe, where <hi>Sillogiſmes must ſeem to uphold the Church:</hi> whereas that which is comprehended within the rules of reaſoning, will fly no higher then reaſon can carry it. Thus doe they ſtrive to place in the Clouds that Article of <hi>I beleeve the holy Catholique Church;</hi> Divine words being ſuch, that they require <hi>a Simple beleever,</hi> but argue <hi>a diſputer impious;</hi> becauſe in Divinity we reſpect not what is ſpoke, but who ſpeaks: How doe the holy vertues of Charity and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37848:79"/> Humility give place to Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heats, and contentions, and tryalls of wit, where men more ſtrive to get the conqueſt in words, then to become the happy ſubjects of truth? Is there no new diſcoveries to be made in the intellectuall Globe? nor means to be found out with the armes of an active reaſon, to inlarge mans dominion over nature? Doth not the <hi>Ethicks</hi> invite a further diſquiſition touching the Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Georgies of the mind, and to finde out Methods of attaining vertue, as well as handſomely to deſcribe it? Doth not the Phyſickes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide you with the few <hi>linkes</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:37848:79"/> that yet men have been able to take up of natures chaine, whereas onely three accidental diſcoveries of Guns, Printing, and the Loadſtone, have alter'd the face of Chriſtendome, in its Wars, Studies, and Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Are the Arts of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves, ſo exact and fit for theſe ſcrutanies, that they need not the help of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelfe to make them more expreſſive and directive: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith, There might be a way of reaſoning found out, wherewith mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inured, they would goe as farre beyond the greateſt Doctor now, as the Learnedeſt Doctor now doth a Childe:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37848:80"/> But I finde it Writ, <hi>That there muſt be Hereſies:</hi> Therefore doubts, ſcruples, and queſtions may breed the ſame diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in mens minds, as <hi>the proſperity of the wicked</hi> did to <hi>David: as ſoon as he entred into the Temple of God, he found an end of them:</hi> where now with pleaſure, we ſhall retire from this noyſe without, and walke into the Gardens of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Spouſe; where we will view the excellent Fruits of Piety, that he himſelfe hath Sowed and Planted there; and which can onely proceed from true Religion. The Antidotes of humane Learning, are many times the Aery Bladders of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37848:80"/> mens Pride, though the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Logicke, object to men their confuſed blindneſſe; the Art of Rhetoricke, their rudeneſſe; the gravity of the <hi>Ethicks,</hi> their paſſionate weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: yet are they pleaſed many times, from them rather to plume themſelves with ſome Feathers of oſtentation, then endevour the reall advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their natures, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it to duty and truth. True Religion ſtabliſhes men in their duties, and conſtitutes the vertues of men from the moſt worthy end of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers prayſe: vertue being elſe but a gathering together of colours, ſeen through the glaſſe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:37848:81"/> of Mens diverſified humors.</p>
            <p>There is no vertue, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Wiſe, Valiant, Sober, Juſt, are Names which none want, which want not vice co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Without this directive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, deſigning all things their Offices, Warre is but an angry fit, and violence taught to undergoe a rule. Courts, and Tribunals, but injuſtice, wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gowne, and putting on the Formalities of Law: all mens ſervices, and moſt obſequious performances, are but well order'd Craft, and methodicall ſubtility: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations of Men, but a Stage, where Vizards are worne with
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:37848:81"/> applauſe: Chaſtity, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of the complexion, and humility but Phlegme. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion fills mens minds with magnanimity, whilſt the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is incited to cenſure worldly things, vaine and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, whereby the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding takes off a true copy of the world; and the cozenages of mens ſoules are prevented, all the inconſtancies which the Scene of humane affaires re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, doe but yeeld a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proſpect to the ſoule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding it ſelfe placed obove the alterable nature of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things; leaving to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire what is inferior, to the dignity of its owne immortall
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37848:82"/> nature; finding that of all the Nymphs men court, be it ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wealth, power, (by a moſt true Metamorphoſis) they catch but an armefull of duſt: for the greatneſſe of mens minds, proceeds from the little eſteeme they have of all ſuch things, as are under the power, and uncertaine ſtroke of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, (that is, of things that by the Laws impoſed on them haſt to change and corruption) for although mens minds may ſeem to be too much buried and depreſt, with the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the diſſolution of things, and in viewing how low all humane hopes doe lye: yet are they thereby truely ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37848:82"/> and elevated; which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept mens minds had buried them, that is, have purſued things to their Tombes and Aſhes; they would have buried mens minds, by ſetting a greater value and rate on things, then their fluid, altering nature would beare. Thus are we cal'd on by Religion, from theſe deluſions from loving the world, or the things in the world: How doth it provide for our contents, lifting up the ſoule, not to any fruitleſſe rocky ſwellings, but to an active towring height, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting mens ſoules, making them take root in Heaven, and to flouriſh downward in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37848:83"/> practice of vertue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, till the cold blaſts of Death breathe on them; when as then thoſe Celeſtiall Spirits repayre to their Mother root, to flouriſh for Eternity? It makes our paſſions the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of vertue, by giving them its directions in their motions, hindring their excur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and fallings out, upon the many falſe ſhewes and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of things. How Heroicall are the commands of Religion? making men the Champions of their neighbours Fame, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverers of the oppreſſed, and every where to erect the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of their Charity; and this upon their Maſters
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37848:83"/> command, with the contempt of the Aery rewards of the World, but ſet on fire with an Heavenly flame, which mens breaths neither kindle, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh: It makes its followers uſe the aydes and comforts of this their exile with ſecurity, in order to ſublimer purchaſes: it makes them ſteddily follow through all ſtates and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their Maſters deſignments, deſiring onely to live in the world in order to his ſervice that made it. It will approach that breaſt with its Celeſtiall purities, which erects a Stage for vain-glorious thoughts to action; or ſets up a Shop for gaine, through covetouſneſſe;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37848:84"/> or ſhambles, for Envy to act its Maſſacres on; or a Taverne for exceſſe and pleaſure. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny devout orders, as it were the Regiments of the Church, that ſight theſe Battles, and exerciſe this holy warfarre? and how many have all of them afforded, either ſtout Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the truth againſt Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; or have ſtored the Church with able and devout Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors; or who have ayded mens devotions, and have kindled mens minds with the love of God, with their ſeraphicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions?<note place="margin">Ieſuits.</note> The orders of Gods Church never growes barren, but are alwayes teeming with the excellencies of tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37848:84"/> gifts. How many ſublime and generous ſpirits, by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent making ſacrifice of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Forraigne parts, makes the hearts of Savages Trophyes of Chriſt Crucified, and fill the Letterd World with the admired productions of Wit and Learning? Here the fire of Devotion is layd upon the true Altar, which never goes out no houre in the Day or Night, where in ſome Church or Convent there are not ſome actually in the Church, offering up their cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Hyms of Prayſe, or mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full throbs of Soule-waſhing Teares, or their ſoules dilated with the flames of burning
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37848:85"/> charity, poure forth their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions. They profeſtly tread under feet the brags of worldly glory: they contemne the dotage of the world, who honour one another in vanity, and ſet a price upon that, which is but the Enſigne of their loſt and falne condition. Here that Hydropick diſtemper of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is conquerd, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a divorce to all propriety: Here, by a generous Flight on the wings of Faſtings and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, their ſoules ſoare above the ſmoke and ſteames of Fleſh and Blood, and breathe in thoſe Upper and purer Regions of Celeſtiall converſation, their ſpirits with diſdaine, deſcend
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:37848:85"/> to moderate repaſts, all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour actions of their life are but rationall diſtinctions, no interruptions from their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they being ſo refined and ſublimed up to ſpirituall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that their converſation, and all the motions and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their heart, doe but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one continued Prayer: Here they follow that councell of <hi>leaving all, and following him:</hi> they view what the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſtianity will coſt; and as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Reſiſt unto blood, proving what the holy and acceptable will of God is.</hi> The Church likewiſe inſtructs its Children, and brings them up in the exerciſe of an active
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:37848:86"/> devotion, as well as contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative, fitted to the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all ſorts of perſons and conditions, making it <hi>ſpeake</hi> in every ones proper and naturall Language; the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Gods ſpirit deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon men (as it were) in ſuch cloven Tongues. Piety and goodneſſe is the end of the Commandement, the will of God being our ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which appeares to triumph in the practice and doctrine of the onely true Catholique Church, of Divine and Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible authority: to the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and demonſtration of which, its agreeable with the Divine goodneſſe to eſtabliſh
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:37848:86"/> the ſame (which is the onely director and care of our way to Heaven) with effectuall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, with a ſucceſſive Prieſthood; the verity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of might be ſhewed as a light upon a Hill, by its univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of place and time: Decrees of Councels, Writings of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and all Antiquity. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath its proper object, and all actions, not ſteared by that compaſſe of obedience, which truth it ſelfe hath enjoyned us, though otherwayes plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, are wound up upon the bottome of error, and turne upon the Poles of erronious and ſelfiſh Principles: as the cleareſt Rivers (which though
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37848:87"/> they delight and profit in their paſſage) yet emptying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a Sea of error, there loſe their name; and the beſt mettall is rung out of tune: notwithſtanding all thoſe who with hearty and faithfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſeek to know how to ſerve God, with a will rather to loſe a thouſand worlds, then not profeſſe what they ſhould know was Gods command. God is at the end of ſuch mens deſires, as he gave them a beginning; and though ſuch be actually in a by channell and way, yet by thoſe. Heavenly inſpirations and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall guſts, they are Sayling out of them into the great Canal.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37848:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
